<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-09T01:00:19-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BLOGS</title><subtitle>Programmar, ex-disc jockey, activist.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">TITLE</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/02/07/Name.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TITLE" /><published>2024-02-07T23:00:22-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-07T23:00:22-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/02/07/Name</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/02/07/Name.html">&lt;p&gt;PARAGRAPH 01!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/MTS.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">PARAGRAPH 01!!!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Free Poems</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/02/01/Poem-01.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free Poems" /><published>2024-02-01T06:00:22-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-01T06:00:22-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/02/01/Poem-01</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/02/01/Poem-01.html">&lt;p&gt;Title: Pain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;There is a pain in my heart,
That doesn&apos;t go far,

There is a pain in my heart,
That has left a bloody scar,

At time, I look at it,
To remind me of you,

Its old, withered and tattered,
Sometimes I wonder how you are,

Time to peel it, with a pocket-knife,
I see new skin, new hope, new life,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Gimme Gimme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Gimme love,
Gimme colors,
Gimme life,

I will drape the sky,
With gloomy lights,

Scented candles and delights,
I will make the heaven filled,

With pool tables, cigars and bar fights,
I will kiss you all day, all night,

Gimme love,
Gimme colors,
Gimme life,

All treasures, assorted dresses and matching carpets,
Will be yours, all is yours, even me and I,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Overcome&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Overcome, overcome it all,
Overcome your addictions,

Alcohol, porn, gambling,
video-games, strippers and motorbikes,

Overcome, overcome it all,
It&apos;s nonetheless then to win a war,

It makes you believe in selfdom,
Gives you worth and a kingdom,

You will learn to fly,
Be the vizier of the sky,

Wind will sing your praises,
And men will bow their hats,

When the sacred touches the soul,
Then the noble heart becomes the goal,

You be on the way to seven valleys,
Where lies the temple of lords,

Have courage, have faith,
Spellbound the heaven gates,

Rise above the blackened cave,
Be ready to kiss her face,

Do not be contend with shadows,
You are man make out of ghettos,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Journey&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The journey is too long,
The journey is too hard,

Your heart be set on fire,
You will loose your mind,

Your bones will break,
Your will be crushed,

How can steps go back,
There is no path to back-track,

A young man must love,
There is nothing above,

You signed up for the ride,
Then why worry of full stride,

I will burn thousand skies,
Just to see her lovely smile,

The air is thin on the top,
The views is meant for a stop,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Title: Pain</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bundle of Poems</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/01/23/Poem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bundle of Poems" /><published>2024-01-23T19:00:22-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-23T19:00:22-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/01/23/Poem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/01/23/Poem.html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the poems I wrote in 2023. Hope the readers find it entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Note: If you do use the poems, please include the author in citation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Earring&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Oh! Oh! my sweet sunshine,
How my heart yearn to see your face,

The lips, the hips, the grace,
In the love of your ways,

Call me if you miss the day,
We sailed across the Hudson Bay,

Rowing, like hands of clock,
Through the trough and crest of waves,

Reminds me of the time,
Lying on floor, listening to your voice,

I pictured you in painting,
Like that girl with pearl earring,

Made my heart to open and sing,
Like the nightingale or a rooster,

Time and space may do us apart,
But your love will always be in my heart,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: On Love&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;There were two lovers,
Mughal and Josephine,

He was made for her,
And she was sent for him,

They were one and the same,
Once breadth was another&apos;s air,

Jospehine beauty and grace,
Made the moon shy and pale,

Mughal courage and justice,
Made the sun into a burning furnace,

No one knows the secret of life,
But true lovers travel through space-time,

The stars danced to the music,
As the Lords made the acoustics,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Ego&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Life is a test,
To see who is best,

To think is to ressurect,
A past ceased in neglect,

Time is gold,
For those grown old,

Rivers flow, destiny bestowed,
What is it all? No one knows,

A man is clay of ego,
A mighty son of sorrow,

Hailed as a king,
Bequeath to a queen,

All she wants,
Is to be heard and seen,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Ol Friends&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;As the train moves through time,
I see life as a blip in existence,

People faces appear and disappear,
Monuments stand tall then vanish,

I have coffee, bread and jam,
Spread on the wooden table,

I sip, I ponder, I gasped,
About times when we chilled,

Talked about guns, cows, and girls,
Smoked till the eyes became blurred,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Man all too man&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Man all too man,
Man all too man,

The world is filled with humans,
None know the point of origin,

Man all too man,
Made of flesh and bones,

Cosmic dust that remains a float,
Like a speck of salt in stale water,

Man built roads, gadgets and gizmos,
Yet no one knows the steps of evolution,

We think we know but do we really think,
Never fear life, as life is a toil,

A toil game that is being and nothingness,
We gasp at the sight of the darkness,

Drawn into abyss like a moth into flames,
Man all too man,

The only test is to survive,
Use can, croony, spoons and every breadth,

To survive and see another daylight,
Time is fleeting, a flux in space-time,

Mind is to think, stomach to eat,
legs to walk and soul to travel,

Society doesn&apos;t have no end,
So go on and do the best you can,

Man all too man,
Man all too man,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Hurt&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Why it hurts,
When you love someone,

Why I dream,
When its not real,

Why I miss you,
When you don&apos;t know me,

Why I await for you,
When you never pass by me,

Why it hurts,
When you love someone,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Loverboy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I will love you,
When it rains,

I will love you,
when it sunny,

I will love you,
When you happy,

I will love you,
When you sad,

I will make you pasta,
With snails and shashimi,

We will eat under a big tree,
Birds will sing accapella,

Dreams are woven,
In your hair curls,

Your body is a coke bottle,
Not fizzled, touched or seen,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Pigeon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The pigeon walk through the meadow,
Seen, smelled, sniffed in the air,

By the wolves, the thieves, the trickster,
They came in compounds, for the final kill,

The pigeon, singed, flocked, pecked,
Then it turned around and check out all the fuss,

Pigeon head was on stick, the wolves ate the guts,
The thieves robbed the bird, and the trickster had an orgy,

Nature is to seek and destroy,
What be said of love and humanity,

A call, a sigh, a signal is send,
A tribe of falcons come to descend,

The evil will be served cold,
The good is on the march of gold,

The simorgh symbol is raised,
Here comes the eagle hand,

The wretched and evil will hide,
The wings of death has come to rise,

The candle, the book, the ode,
Note to note the winds play joy,

The sun will rise from east,
The moon will die in the west,

Not one or the other chosen for best,
The pigeon makes for a good dinner flesh,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title: Road Dogs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Its time for me to go,
To be back on the road,

Its time for us to depart,
You will always be in my heart,

Its been good, it was good,
Ten years we here and stood,

Your scent, shrubs and honeydew,
I will reminiscence and be blue,

So long the smoke,drink, and phuddi,
Don&apos;t act as if you knew me,

The hermit must travel on,
Into solemn, cold and ugly storm,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">These are the poems I wrote in 2023. Hope the readers find it entertaining.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Freedom Fries</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/10/07/Freedom-Fries.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Freedom Fries" /><published>2023-10-07T03:05:22-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-07T03:05:22-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/10/07/Freedom-Fries</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/10/07/Freedom-Fries.html">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fries are a universal language. If you travel around the modern world there is a definite chance of finding fries. The first time I saw fries was on a busy Pakistani street. There was a kid in green shalwar and kameez (traditional dress) with a cart and an oil heating tub. The tub seemed as an electronic rice cooker. There was certain amount of oil with laces of potatoes swimming in the pot. The fries were delicious. Crispy, salty,long and hot. Then as time went on, I found fries to become an accessory to meals rather then a main dish. Whether it was a burger, fried chicken, fish entre, salad bowl, meat on a stick, milkshake or a bakery product, I always have fries on the side. In simple terms: No freedom, no fries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, me and my Belgian buddy were discussing about fries. He told me that even though the food is fully named as “french fries”, it has nothing to do with France. The origin of fries is Belgian not France. I didn’t venture in the origin story further, so I took his word. It does make sense as Belgians are known for their love of fries. Just as in Pakistan you can find a chai stall on every street, similarly, you will find a fries cart on every Belgian road. Belgium is also known as the “battleground of Europe.” Due to its location and resources, major European powers have fought on its soil to retrieve the banner as the sovereign and ultimate power. The famous battles are as follows: Battle of Oudenaarde (1708, Dutch win against the French forces), Battle of Ramilies (1706, Loss of French empire against the British troops), Battle of Waterloo (1815, Napolean lost his last battle to Coalition forces and was exiled to Saint Helena), Battle of Ypres ( 1914, World War I, approximately million soldiers died), Battle of Bastogne (1944, World War II, US victory against Nazis) etc [1]. I wondered if the triumph party had fries for celebration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every generation is impacted by warfare. Millineals will remember the Iraq war (2003-2011), Afghan War (2001-2021), Syrian War, Yemen War and the recent Ukraine War. What makes a war justified? Can there be any justification for such horrendous acts? Is there such a thing as theory of war? These questions lead us to the infamous ‘just theory of war’ [2]. The theory is a doctrine or set of principles that must be met to justify a state to venture into warfare. But after scrutiny we find that just war theory tells us nothing important. It can be placed in three simple questions: Should I go to war or not? How should I conduct the war? what is the general outcome of the war? I will now deal with each question, individually.  There are two schools of thought which focuses on the justification aspect, the Groatian tradition of war and the Rousseau’s republican tradition of war [3]. The Groatian tradition stems from the ideas of Hugo Grotius. He was a dutch scholar who is considered as the pioneer of international law. This tradition places war in theoretical framework and uses universal principles or international bodies, such as: UNO or Security Council to dictate the validation of war. I think Grotius ideas fall short for two reasons. First, the universal principles are not clear. There is no clear path or set of rules to follow. It is good to have the laws of war not set in stones as every situation is different and varies greatly. But different interpretation leads to different results and as such the theory can not be verified for its results. Secondly, Grotius is treated as an enigma due to unclarity or vagueness in his thoughts and ideas. This also stems from his merging of theological principles with laws of war, that leads to unclear conclusions. Though his ideas do carry influence as in modern world decisions of war are taken through plural discourse rather then singular motives. Such as: UN, NATO, EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other tradition is based on romantic thoughts of Rousseau. This dictates that war is justified if it is for liberty, equality, revolt against tyranny, freedom of minority, individual rights etc. This traditon is broadly guided through emotions rather then rigid principles. This school of thought is known as &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Republic Tradition of War&lt;/code&gt;, as it emphasises on the actions of elected state representatives and constitutional guidelines. Rousseau placed great emphasis on the individual. His main premise was that the human nature at core is good and peaceful. It is when the man inter-mingles with society that he loses his true nature and becomes dumb, docile and generic. He amalgamates with the culture rather then challange it. Once the selfdom is removed from the man, then he follows the commands of the State. The state dictates the enemies and the warfare. The man ends up being a spectator or participant for an uninformed goal. Rousseau firmly believed that the noblest quality in a man’s life is freedom. It is to live with no constraint, control or subjugation to an empire. Once a man is free then he can express himself and criticize the ruling class. The philosopher emphasized that the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;justification&lt;/code&gt; aspect of any war lies in the heart or subjective view of candidate. Further, the tyrant is mostly the one which initiates the war. It is for the candidate to think, reflect, judge and decide whether the war is justified. The only downside to this notion is what if the man is wrong is his conclusion? There is a large possibility that the man is compelled to war due to racist, prejudice, revenge or self-interest rather then clear reasoning, logical deduction or ideas based on facts. Another aspect to the republican tradition is revolution. This occurs when the oppressed party take arms and action against the tyrannical rulers. As Rousseau states [4]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; I see unfortunate peoples wailing about from beneath an iron
yoke, the frst human race crushed by a handful of oppressors;a mob painfully overworked and
starving for bread—the blood and tears of whom the rich drink in peace—and everywhere the
strong armed against the weak with the formidable power of the laws. All of this was accomplished peacefully and without resistance: it’s the tranquility of Ulysses’s companions locked up
in Cyclops’s cavern, waiting to be devoured.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rousseau admired the works of Pasquale Paoli (1725 - 1807) and Tadeusz Kosciuzko (1746 - 1817). Paoli was the President of Corsica and the military leader who fought against the aggressions of the French State. Corsica is a small island in the south seas of France. King Louis XV wanted to annex Corsica to strengthen the French presence and kingdom. Paoli tried his utmost to keep his land free from foreign domination but his efforts were futile. The French forces were able to defeat Corsican in decisive battles. Still, Paoli is remembered as a liberterian and protagonist who stood against the tyrants. Tadeusz, on the other hand, was a Polish soldier who fought against the Russian influence. He is widely remembered who led and won victories against the Russian army, even though Tadeusz had smaller army and limited resources. Rousseau coveted these men, as they stood for liberty, and fought against ruling elites. Another example, in our modern times, is of Soviet Union annexation of Afghanistan (1979 - 1989) or the Vietnam War (1955 - 1975). In both wars, the oppressed were victorious against the oppressors. Rousseau would be delighted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find that the real world is much complicated and mostly lies in the middle of these opposing traditions. (Can there be a matrix diagram that shows different options of just war theory?). Rule of thumb is: Follow your gut feeling. It does sound mundane, rudimentary and naive but sometimes the simplest answer is the best answer. 90% of the times, the transgressors are the culprits. 10% lies in the grey area. A good-example of the grey area is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ukraine War&lt;/code&gt;. Though Russia is the aggressor and the first notion is to label Russia as the culprit, but the conclusion is superficial. Just as West feels threatened by a strong Russian coalition, similarly Russia feels threatened with NATO expansion in it’s proximity. It must be remembered that I am not supporting the actions of Putin but I am trying to argue whether the war is justified or unjustified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part of Just War is the conduct. How should the war be conducted? Carl Von Clausewitz (1780 - 1831) wrote a seminal work on the topic, named “On War”. Clausewitz was a general in the Prussian army that fought against Napolean forces. He is famously quoted for “ War is the continutation of State’s policy by other means.” Politics and War are opposite part of the same coin. If one state can’t achieve its aim through political discourse then it uses physical or Lenin stated to use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;forcible means&lt;/code&gt; to achieve its objectives. Clausewitz emphasized that every war is different and the leader must prepare each aspect of the war, tentatively. The author stressed on the highest priority of every individually is simply freedom. He wrote [5]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; I Believe and Profess that a people never must value a thing higher than the dignity 
 and freedom of its existence; that it must defend these with the last drop of its blood; 
 that it has no duty more sacred and can obey no law that is higher; that the shame 
 of a cowardly submission can never be wiped out; thta the posion of submission in the bloodstream of a people will be transmitted to its children, 
 and paralyze and undermine the strength of later generations;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rousseau will also support this claim as it relates to human nature of freedom, liberty and selfdom. Though war is a reality of human affairs, it must be kept as the last option. Only those who have participated or seen the consequences of war, will tell us the horrendous reality of warfare. It is a catastrophe that can be abated only through diplomacy, wisdom and a bit of luck. But if all else fails, strapping the bullet belt seems to be the last resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last part of Just War is the Justice after war or peace-building. This part occurs after the war is ended and the restoration of human life is to be initiated. Although, this part is not considered and less attention is payed. This is still important to understand and reconcile because war directly or indirectly impacts every citizen on the participates. Further the common citizens normal life, lifestock and environment is devastated. It requires international effort and the confronting states to reconcile, formulate peace treaties and initiate the building process. Mostly, we find the belligerants leave the weakened state and let them handle the calamities. No remorse or consideartion is shown. Human nature at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] https://www.quora.com/Why-is-Belgium-called-the-European-battlefield&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just_war_theory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] http://ndl.ethernet.edu.et/bitstream/123456789/25395/1/42.pdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] J.J. Rousseau, Principles of the Right of War&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] Edward M. Collins, War, Politics &amp;amp; Power&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chomsky Rebuttal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/08/14/Chomsky.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chomsky Rebuttal" /><published>2023-08-14T22:58:22-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-14T22:58:22-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/08/14/Chomsky</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/08/14/Chomsky.html">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may agree with Noam Chomsky or disagree with him, but you can not ignore him. I have been influenced by the philosopher since high school days. He is the silent revolutionary. I don’t know of any other intellectual, in modern times, to have impacted the world as Mr. Noam has done. An individual is judged by what he says and what he does. Mr. Chomsky has always done what he preaches. As being a scientist, he pursues all his topics with the same ferver, logical deductions and plethora of facts. As being an intellect, he has challanged the status quo. Noam is a hero that stood against the bullies and defended the public citizen. He wears no cape and has no super power. He is a man that uses his voice of reason with no constraints and his intellectual curiosity that is beyond bounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As all great minds, they go through phases. In early days, Noam created a whole field in computational linguistics (which I still have to study further). Then in 70s, he became more active in political hemisphere. His writing on Vietnam War, Neoliberalism, Class Warfare, and public democracy  are considered classic works in social science and have become associated with Chomskyism (if the word can be used). Now, Chomsky acts as an arbiter or pamphleteer on global stage. He makes things simple to understand, promotes sensible policies and creates disctinction between good and bad actions. He is the Plato for the millennials. Its still too early to judge his work, but time will display the depth, influence and impact of what the professor accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chomksy notion of three existential threat to humanity has become my world-view of the present state of our society. It states that there are three things that can destroy biological life on this planet: Global Warming, Nuclear Warfare and Neoliberal policies. Global warming or climate change has become a reality. The earths temparture is increasing, the weather is becoming unpredictable, animals are becoming extinct at a faster rate and the sea level is on the rise. This year alone I can count dozen reports in which the climate change was having devastating consequences on humanity. For example: Canada and Hawaii wildfires, Arizona’s 120 farenheit temperature, smoke and dust clouds in New York City and rain floods in the southern states. Scientist have been warning the Congress and government since 70s regarding the temperature rise due to fossil fuels usage [1]. But the political response has been slow and cumbersome to these issues. There are still climate change denialist which is a problem in itself. The next threat on the list is Nuclear Warfare, aka: Nukes. Nukes are weapons that uses the energy from splitting atoms to create explosions. These are more then explosions as the core of atom bombs can reach million of degrees. Imagine what happen to a human or living being in amid of the detonation. US is the country which created the technology in the 40s (due to the scare of Nazi Germany working on nuclear technology). Then US did a demo test on Japan Hiroshima and Nagasaki (further study is required on the lasting impact of the event). Throughout the years about 7 countries have been able to create their own nuclear weapons, with a stockpile reaching close to 13000 weapons [2]. Currently there is no sign of slowing down with the generation and distribution of such weapons. Major war lines are being drawn through out the world, such as: Russia-Ukraine war, China-Taiwan confrontation, Pak-India disputes etc. Nukes will have a devastating consequence if used by any of the countries. It is a ticking bomb indeed. The last threat on the list is neoliberal policies. This is a subtle issue which is difficult to contemplate or decipher. Essentially, Chomsky states it as a control of the working class by technocrats or the people in power. I see that America has shifted from an egalitarian society to a corporate society. Back in day, the middleclass used to be stronger, vibrant and intellectual. Now it is being shrunked and it is wrapped in the game of money. The corporation are the new rulers and have a large control on the lives of its workers. That is the reason for weaker union labours throughout the country and stringent policies. As stated, neoliberal and the concept is hard to understand but it can be seen through the lens of corporation and its autonomy to do as it pleases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chomsky is considered the father of modern linguistics. I have not studied his major works or theorems but I do have a high-level understanding of his ideas. Firstly, language is not learned (as mostly conceived) but it is pre-programmed in humans. It is widely believed that as a person learns to swim or write, the same mechanics are involved in language acquisition. Chomsky states that language is a form of biological endowment specific to humans. It is as if it is in our genetics to use language. A good example is a baby learning language. No one gives a baby a set of methods or grammatical rules before starting to speak. The toddler simply watches others using words and sees objects around him. He uses instinctive queues and language pattern to express himself. Naturally he learns to use words or speak a certain language. If the parents are English native, then he/she will learn the particular language. The origin of language is still debated and further research is required to understand this phenomenon [3]. Modern pundits state that origin of language is stemmed in biology. There was a need to express human thoughts and thus through trial and error, humanity stumbled on language. That can be a part of the origins but doesn’t provide complete picture.  It seems the use of langauge is inifinite. As thoughts are infinite so is the usage of the language. This is known as the Galileo challange or paradox [4]. More research is required within this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the attribute that I most admire about Mr. Chomsky is his unrelenting quest to always speak the truth, regardless of the group of powers and authority he is up against. This is a sign of a true hero. The person who protects and defends the weak against the bully. All Marvel Comic heroes don’t compare to the courage, valour and intellect of the modern sage. When in doubt, always ask what will Noam do in this condition? Then do the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] https://www.zinnedproject.org/news/tdih/james-hansen-testified-senate-climate-change/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] https://www.ucsusa.org/nuclear-weapons/worldwide#:~:text=Nine%20countries%20possess%20nuclear%20weapons,is%20close%20to%2013%2C000%20weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] https://www.santafe.edu/research/projects/the-origins-evolution-and-diversity-of-human-langu&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] https://inference-review.com/article/the-galilean-challenge&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>